Guide to the Peter F. O'Brien Collection on African American Writers and Performers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter F. O'Brien collection on African American artists
1940-1998
JWJ MSS 99
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.51
(6 boxes)
The collection contains material compiled by Father Peter F. O'Brien on twentieth century African American cultural figures. The collection consists chiefly of subject files on prominent mid-century artists, authors, and performers, including stage and screen actors, singers, and dancers. Individuals covered include: James Baldwin, Paul Robeson, Antonio Salemme, Ethel Waters, Mabel Mercer, and Thelma Carpenter, among others. Files contain printed materials, such as newspaper clippings and programs and playbills for productions, letters, and photographs.
O'Brien, Peter F. (Peter Francis)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter F. O'Brien, 1994-1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Peter F. O'Brien
Father Peter F. O'Brien, S.J., is a Roman Catholic priest and a member of The Society of Jesus. Also a noted jazz historian, Father O'Brien managed the musical career of Mary Lou Williams from 1970 to 1981 and serves as Executive Director of The Mary Lou Williams Foundation. He teaches English composition at St. Peter's College in Jersey City, New Jersey and is a chaplain for Compassionate Care Hospice.
Biographical information taken from the Mary Lou Williams Foundation website, <http://marylouwilliams.org/contact.htm>, accessed 8 January 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains material compiled by Father Peter F. O'Brien on twentieth-century African American cultural figures. The collection consists chiefly of subject files on prominent mid-century artists, authors, and performers, including stage and screen actors, singers, and dancers. Individuals covered include: James Baldwin, Paul Robeson, Antonio Salemme, Ethel Waters, Mabel Mercer, and Thelma Carpenter, among others. Files contain printed materials, such as newspaper clippings and programs and playbills for productions, letters, and photographs.
Arrangement
Orgnaized chronologically into five groupings by date of acquisition: I. February 1994 Acquisition. II. March 1994 Acquisition. III. November 1994 Acquisition. IV. January 1995 Acquisition. V. March 1998 Acquisition.
African American actors; African American dancers; African American singers; American literature -- African American authors; American literature -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Baldwin, James, 1924-1987; Carpenter, Thelma, (Vocalist); O'Brien, Peter F. (Peter Francis); Mercer, Mabel, 1900-1984; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Salemme, Antonio, 1892-1995; Waters, Ethel, 1896-1977
- I. February 1994 Acquisition, 1940-1992; 0.7; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The February 1994 Acquisition contains subject files on African American culture and performers. The files consist chiefly of printed materials, including newspaper clippings and programs and playbills for productions, but letters and photographs are also present.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 316.
  - PMLA issue, 1990 January (Box 1)
  - "Salemme-Robeson", 1948-1977, undated (Box 1)
  - "Carl Van Vechten", 1955-1974, undated (Box 1)
  - "Drawings", 1975 (Box 1)
  - "James Baldwin", 1974-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - "Ethel Waters", 1964-1991, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - "Mabel Mercer", 1964-1984, undated (Box 1)
  - "African American Theatre", 1942-1986, undated (Box 1)
  - "Paul Padgette", 1974 (Box 1)
  - "Approved Budget 1980-1981", 1969-1983, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - "Diana Sands", 1968-1977, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - "Various Artists", undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - "Gilbert Price +Bruce Hubbard", 1940-1991, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - "Harlem On My Mind", 1968, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - "Int. Re Ethel Waters + Van Vechten", 1992 (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - "Obits: Count Basie...", 1984, undated (Box 2 (Oversize))
  - Life issue, 1964 May 29 (Box 2 (Oversize))
- II. March 1994 Acquisition, 1964-1985; 0.21; (1 box)
  The March 1994 Acquisition contains additional printed materials and photogaphs relating to African American culture and performers.
  Former call number: Uncat Za MS 395.
  - Miscellaneous material relating to African American culture, 1964-1985, undated (Box 3)
- III. November 1994 Acquisition, 1965-1989; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subgroupings: Correspondence and Subject Files.
  The November 1994 Acquisition contains letters to Peter O'Brien and additional clippings files.
  Former call number: Uncat Za MS 421.
  - Correspondence
    - Carpenter, Thelma, 1970 April 19 (Box 4)
    - Harris, Julie, 1969 November 18 (Box 4)
    - Lucioni, Luigi, undated (Box 4)
    - Padgette, Paul, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Salemme, Antonio; Salemme, Martha, 1965, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Subject Files
    - Graham, Billy, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Lundy, Carmen, 1983-1987 (Box 4)
    - Van Vechten, Carl, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Waters, Ethel, 1970-1989, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1970, undated (Box 4)
- IV. January 1995 Acquisition, 1964-1994; 0.21; (1 box)
  The January 1995 Acquistion contains mixed clippings files on African American cultural figures.
  Former call number: Uncat Za MS 429.
  - "Mabel Mercer + Ethel Waters", 1964-1972 (Box 5)
  - "Gilbert Price, Other Theatre + Film Pieces...", 1964-1994 (Box 5)
  - "Van Dyke-Salemme-Banks-Anselm-Fania Van Vechten", 1964-1972 (Box 5)
  - "Diana Sands + Thelma Carpenter", 1964-1971 (Box 5)
- V. March 1998 Acquisition, 0.21; (1 box)
  The March 1998 Acquisition contains printed material relating to the 1998 stage production of "Mamba's Daughters" by Dorothy and DuBose Heyward.
  Former call number: Uncat JWJ MS 62.
  - Miscellaneous material relating to "Mamba's Daughters", 1998; 2 (Box 6)